Boolean operators.
Now that's another big word that you can little phrase you can throw around.
We mentioned boolean earlier.
And really that's just fancy computer talk for when things are logical.
And they're conditions that you can have like in Ands and ORS and things like that.
So they're very useful because often in life we need to say, well if this and that is true if this
or that is true.
And so we want to show you a little example where maybe we've got a club or something.
And you we want to charge people based on the age, whether they can come in and watch the movies here
or do some dancing or whatever it might be.
But there's two things that are going to impact the ticket price of entry, and one is the age, and
the other one is whether you remember.
So we can whatever that means based on your age.
If your age is a certain range, you're going to get a different price.
And obviously if you're a member which is a Boolean value, true or false, it's going to also impact
your price.
So we're going to set up our if and our else.
But you're going to see we're going to use more than one condition here and we're going to use ranges.
So let's start.
So let's say if the age of the person is maybe I don't know, let's say little kids less than or equal
to five, then they are going to be free.
So we're going to print, you know price is free or whatever is free.
So we're just going to now basically.
Okay.
So then next is so that's the first one.
Now we want to do an Elsif and check.
Well if the age is from six.
So it's going to be greater than or equal to six.
But if it's between six and let's say uh I don't know let's pick a teenagers 13.
So we now have a range.
So we need to check if they are greater than or equal to six and less than the age of 13.
So what you'll notice here though is for each condition you want to check, you have to write out this
full statement.
I can't just say if the age is greater than or equal to six, and then ignore this part here and say
and less than or less than 13, you have to rewrite the whole statement you want to check.
So you have to type if your age is greater than six.
And then I also want to check if the age is less than 13.
And the reason for that is because that second test age less than 13, we don't have to use the variable
age.
We could have used something else, as we'll show you in a moment.
So in this case we've actually created a range.
So we're going to print price is $5 or whatever it is.
So again we are not checking a range.
So we're using this boolean connector this.
And to actually check a range.
So now we're going to do another Elsif and say okay else if the age is greater or equal to 13.
So we've got to capture the 13 and let's go up to I don't know what our pension age is probably 60 less
than age less than 60.
And this is going to be the full price person.
So print price is $10.
It's a bargain for coming in and watching a movie on the big screen in our club that we've set up.
So their price is now the full $10.
Right now we now want to check our fourth category, and our fourth category is going to be something
slightly special.
So our fourth category is for our pensioners.
So if the age is greater or equal to 60 that's our pensioners.
They are going to get this at a super duper bargain price of let's say, what are the pensioners going
to get?
I don't think they care.
How about a dollar?
Okay.
That's fantastic.
They get a special price of $1.
This is an excellent club to visit.
But it's not just the pensioners you see now.
What you don't realise is, if you remember, you also get the pensioner price.
Now that is amazing.
So we need to have two conditions in here.
So not only if the age is greater than 60 but all member is equal to true.
So this is important now because this is an Or statement which means either one of these can be true.
Either the age is greater than or equal to 60, in which case it's going to print.
The price is $1 or member is equal to true.
And then it's also going to print.
The price is equal to $1.
If it was an and statement then that would obviously mean that both had to be true for it to print this
price as $1.
But yeah.
So it's an all.
So either of these can be true.
What you might also have noticed is we used a new thing that we haven't before is that we check that
if this variable is equal to true, which is a boolean value.
So by doing this, it's basically doing exactly what we have in all our other things.
But instead of checking it against a value it's checking if it is true.
So if the member is equal to true then do this.
Else if it is not equal to true, then don't do it.
So basically it's just checking if it is true or if it's not true.
And based on that it will either print this or not.
So note this is a special type of variable.
Remember we talked about we've got a number variables or integers.
In this case this is a boolean variable.
It just has two values false or true.
Don't put it in inverted commas that would convert into string.
This is not a string.
It is a basically used for testing trues and falses.
So you can see the color of that how it's changed.
And here as well.
So it recognizes that a boolean is either a true or a false.
So what's left to finish us off?
What are we missing?
Well, remember, we've got to have the catchall.
So we would need an else statement to say what happens if none of these are true?
And maybe we'll say, you know, error in age or whatever or error entry or just something, you know,
just capturing that they've entered something in correctly in the entry.
Okay.
So now let's run it.
We have set our age is equal to 20.
So it's gone through all of these.
And if you try and find the right condition yourself, you'll see that this is the one that evaluates
to true.
Because 20 is greater than 13 and 20 is less than 60.
So it is printed down here.
The price is $10.
Now let's just change this to another age.
Let's try it with five.
Oh, there we go.
Price is free.
So this all looks like it's working absolutely fantastic.
So I know let's try and make them a member.
So let's change member to true.
So really what should happen is it should say their price is $1 free.
What?
That is crazy.
No, but we want it to be that they're a member.
But you see what's happening here.
And in this case.
Okay, so the member has has scored and that's that's great.
But if the member had a higher age like 55 and they should be getting a free, they're not they're getting
a price of $10 because it is evaluating 55 between the age of 13 and 60.
So what's happening here is remember your program starts working from the top.
It works its way down.
So it checks that nope.
Not true.
It checks that nope.
Checks that yes, it is true.
Prints that and ignores the rest.
So it actually doesn't even get you to check.
Oh, but if member is true, we should be having a price of $1.
So we need to add something else.
We need to make sure that when it checks the ages, it checks as well that they are not a member because
the member is a different price range.
Now, obviously we wouldn't have to apply that to the less than five because that's obviously irrelevant.
That's free whether you're a member or not.
But from this point on, from that 6 to 13 and the next one, we need to check whether they're a member
or not.
To do that, we just have to add in another and statement.
So for this, we want to check if between these ages and their member status is false.
And I didn't do a double equal.
Okay.
So we've checked now.
That's the age.
And they're not a member.
And again here we want to check.
So we basically now copy and paste.
The fun thing is we're actually putting multiple conditions and this is what you can increasingly do.
You can get quite involved.
So essentially now this should work.
So we run it.
And yes price is $1.
Because what it's doing is even though the age 55 fell into the category 13 to 60, that part was true.
But the third condition wasn't true because they have members equal to true.
And this says member must equal to false.
So that entire condition was rejected and it moved on to the final category.
And it said is age greater than or equal to 60 or member is true that one is true because they're a
member.
And so the price is $1.
So you can see where the logic comes into this.
You really have to be thinking, but it's okay to make mistakes if things don't work out immediately.
You look at it, you think about it and you can figure out what's going on.
So this is our if else ifs and putting boolean conditions together, it gets quite exciting.
And these things are all going to come into play when we write our game later on.